A Finding Aid to the Ben Shahn Papers, 1879-1990, bulk 1933-1970, in the Archives of American Art AAA.shahben
Archives of American Art
Ben Shahn papers
bulk 1933-1970
1879-1990
AAA.shahben
Archives of American Art
24.6 Linear feet
The papers of social realist painter, photographer, illustrator, printmaker, and teacher Ben Shahn (1898-1969) measure 24.6 linear feet and date from 1879-1990, with the bulk of the material dating from 1933-1970. The bulk of the collection consists of over 14 linear feet of incoming letters from artists, writers, colleagues, publishers, art organizations, galleries, and universities and colleges. Also found are biographical materials, project and source files, printed material, artwork by Shahn and others, photographs taken of and by Shahn, interview transcripts, and audio and video recordings.
Shahn, Ben
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Ben Shahn papers were donated in several installments between 1967-1991 by Shahn's widow, Bernarda Bryson Shahn.
Separated Materials note
In 1969, Bernarda Bryson Shahn loaned addresses and essays by Shahn, 7 royalty statements, and 3 letters from publishers for microfilming. After filming, the material was returned to the donor. The loaned material is available on 35 mm microfilm reel N70-6 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan, which is not described in the container list of this finding aid. However, many of Shahn's writings on this microfilm were included in subsequent donations to the Archives of American Art.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art holds four oral history interviews with Ben Shahn: 1964 Apr. 14 interview conducted by Richard K. Doud for the Archives of American Art New Deal and the Arts Project in which Shahn speaks of his travels and work for the Farm Security Administration (FSA) and the American image as portrayed by FSA; 1965 Jan. 17 interview; 1965 Oct. 3. interview conducted by Harlan Phillips for the Archives of American Art New Deal and the Arts Project; and 1968 Sept. 27 interview conducted by Forrest Selvig. Most of these interviews have transcripts available online.
The Archives also holds the Bernarda Bryson Shahn papers, circa 1947-2005, and two oral history interviews with Bernarda Bryson Shahn: 1983 Apr. 29 and 1995 July 3.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This site provides access to the papers of Ben Shahn in the Archives of American Art that were digitized in 2010, and total 41733 images.
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Ben Shahn (1898-1969) was a social realist painter, muralist, printmaker, photographer, illustrator, and teacher who worked primarily in Brooklyn, New York and New Jersey. He was most active in the 1930s through the 1950s and worked on several federally funded arts projects, including the Farm Security Administration's photographic documentation project of rural America during the Depression.
Ben Shahn was born in Kovno, Lithuania and immigrated with his family to the United States in 1906 where he settled in Brooklyn, and later Roosevelt, New Jersey, after becoming a naturalized citizen in 1918.
Following an apprenticeship as a lithographer from 1913-1917, Shahn studied at New York University, the City College of New York, and the National Academy of Design from 1919-1922. He married Tillie Goldstein in 1922 and they had two children, Judith and Ezra.
Two years after Shahn's first solo exhibition at the Downtown Gallery in 1930, his Passion of Sacco and Vanzetti, a series of 23 gouaches about the Sacco and Vanzetti trial of the 1920s, was exhibited at the Downtown Gallery to critical and public acclaim. The exhibition marked the beginning of Shahn's reputation as one of the most important social realist painters in America. Shahn's commitment to social and political justice found a natural outlet in mural painting when, in 1933, he was hired to assist Diego Rivera on the labor and industry mural Man at the Crossroads, for New York City's Rockefeller Center. The mural was destroyed amid controversy in 1933 before it was completed, but Shahn had learned much about the art of fresco painting during the project and was inspired by the potential of the mural as a unique art form for presenting life's struggles and stories to a large public audience. Between 1933 and 1937 Shahn worked on various murals for other buildings, including New York's Central Park Casino (circa 1934) and Riker's Island Prison (1934), none of which saw completion. In 1937, however, the Farm Security Administration (FSA) commissioned Shahn to execute a mural for the Community Center in the town of Jersey Homesteads, later Roosevelt, New Jersey, which Shahn completed in 1938. Shahn settled in Jersey Homesteads the following year and remained there for the rest of his life. Other important mural commissions followed for the Bronx Central Post office (1939) and the Social Security Building in Washington DC (1942).
One of Shahn's assistants on the Jersey Homesteads mural was Bernarda Bryson, whom he had met in 1933 when she came to New York to interview Rivera about the Rockefeller Center mural controversy for an Ohio newspaper. Shahn and Bryson became lifetime companions and had three children, Susanna, Jonathan and Abigail, although they did not marry until shortly before Shahn's death in 1969. Shahn and Tillie Goldstein were divorced in 1944.
Shahn had enrolled with the federal Public Works of Art Project in 1934, and between 1935 and 1938 he and Bryson travelled across country as Shahn photographed poverty-stricken areas and documented rural life for the Farm Security Administration (FSA) and the Resettlement Agency. Shahn's interest in photography developed in the early 1930s when, encouraged by his friendship with Walker Evans, he began photographing street scenes and people in New York City. He later used the images as the basis for many of his prints and paintings.
In 1942 Shahn began working for the Office of War Information (OWI) and was instructed to produce posters and pamphlets explaining to citizens the necessities of wartime, such as the need for secrecy and food rationing. Ultimately, only two of Shahn's posters were ever used; the rest were rejected as being too harsh for their intended audience. Shahn later worked for the Congress of Industrial Organization Political Action Committee (CIO-PAC), producing posters for the 1944 campaign to re-elect Roosevelt, who he believed in deeply. He was promoted to director of the CIO's Graphic Arts Division for the 1946 congressional campaign following Roosevelt's death, but that job ended when the election went poorly for the Democratic party.
Shahn returned increasingly to painting and a retrospective of his work was held at the Museum of Modern Art in 1947. He also became more active in academia as an accomplished writer, teacher and lecturer. He received honorary doctorates from Princeton University and Harvard University, and become the Charles Eliot Norton professor at Harvard in 1956. Shahn's Norton lectures were collected and published as the influential The Shape of Content in 1957. He also began to work as a commercial artist for a variety of companies and publications including CBS, Time, Harper's, and the Container Corporation of America. Shahn believed, however, that the artist's ideas and integrity must always be reflected in his commercial art. He refused to compromise on this point and was very selective in his choice of commercial commissions. Shahn illustrated many books and articles, designed sets for stage productions such as New York Export: Opus Jazz, choreographed by Jerome Robbins, and designed mural mosaics for synagogues, universities and private homes.
Since the 1930s Shahn had been represented by Edith Halpert at the Downtown Gallery, but his relationship with her was always contentious on the subject of payments Shahn received for commercial work, and became increasingly so as his income from such sources increased. Finally, in 1968, Shahn wrote to Halpert telling her that after ten years of "an accumulation of ill-feeling, discomfort and recrimination between us" he felt compelled to end their dealer-artist relationship.
By the time of Shahn's break with Halpert his health had begun to fail. He died of a heart attack following surgery in a New York City hospital on March 14, 1969.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of social realist painter, photographer, illustrator, printmaker, and teacher Ben Shahn (1898-1969) measure 24.6 linear feet and date from 1879-1990, with the bulk of the material dating from 1933-1970. The bulk of the collection consists of over 14 linear feet of incoming letters from artists, writers, colleagues, publishers, art organizations, galleries, and universities and colleges. Also found are biographical materials, project and source files, printed material, artwork by Shahn and others, photographs taken of and by Shahn, interview transcripts, and audio and video recordings.
Biographical material and family records include a 1924 passport for Shahn and his first wife, Tillie, biographical sketches of Shahn, and award certificates received by him.
Letters are primarily written to Shahn from family members, artists, writers, colleagues, publishers, art organizations, galleries, and universities and colleges. Notable correspondents include Leonard Baskin, Alexander Calder, Dorothea Lange, Walker Evans, Joseph Hirsch, Leo Lionni, John Bartlow Martin, George and Marian Nakashima, Clifford Odets, Charles Olson, Robert Osborn, Diego Rivera, Jerome Robbins, Selden Rodman, James Thrall Soby, Raphael Soyer, and William Carlos Williams. A small number of scattered letters from Shahn can also be found throughout the series.
Project files document approximately twenty-one of Shahn's commissions, including murals for the community center at Jersey Homesteads, the Bronx Central Annex Post Office, the Social Security Building in Washington D.C., and the William E. Grady Vocational High School. The files also document his involvement in the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial in Roosevelt, in addition to projects for schools, temples and private homes.
Financial and legal records include consignment records, loan agreements, royalty statements and receipts for artwork sold.
Notes and writings are by Shahn and others including Alan Dugan, W. H. Ferry, Theodore Gusten, and John Bartlow Martin. They include lists of artwork, many of which are annotated.
Artwork includes a sketchbook and several unbound sketches and lettering by Shahn, in addition to drawings and prints by others including Shahn's children, Mario Casetta and Stefan Martin.
Source files contain printed material and photographs relating to topics depicted by Shahn in his artwork such as children, dams, farming, houses, industry, mines and miners, slums, war and workers. These files also contain scattered photographic prints by FSA and OWI photographers including Shahn, Jack Delano, Walker Evans, Dorothea Lange, Russell Lee, Carl Mydans, Marion Post Wolcott, Arthur Rothstein, and John Vachon.
Printed material includes news clippings covering Shahn and his career as well as subjects of interest to Shahn. Also found are exhibition catalogs and announcements for exhibitions for Shahn and others, and reproductions of Shahn's artwork including publications illustrated by him.
Photographs are of Shahn, his family and friends and colleagues including Alexander Calder, Jerome Robbins, Charles Sheeler, David Smith and William Zorach. Also included are photographs taken by Shahn of New York City and for the FSA in the 1930s, as well as photographs of artwork by Shahn. Photographs by others include one photo each by Walker Evans, Dorothea Lange, Russell Lee and Arthur Rothstein.
The collection also contains transcripts of eight radio, television and motion picture interviews of Shahn and a reel of 16mm motion picture film transferred to VHS from the BBC-TV program "Monitor," in addition to three reels of audio tape interviews of Shahn by Tony Schwartz and Arlene Francis. Artifacts include a Christmas greeting in the form of a sock.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 12 series:
Series 1: Biographical and Family Records, 1879-1984 (Box 1, OV 36; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 2: Letters, 1929-1990 (Boxes 1-25, 35, OVs 36-38; 14.4 linear ft.)
Series 3: Project Files, 1933-1975 (Boxes 25-26; OVs 36-37; 1.03 linear ft.)
Series 4: Financial and Legal Records, 1934-1988 (Boxes 26-27, 35; 0.81 linear ft.)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, circa 1933-1988 (Boxes 27-28; 1.62 linear ft.)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1930s-1965 (Boxes 28, 35; 11 folders)
Series 7: Source Files, circa 1900s-1960s (Boxes 28-30, 35; 1.81 linear ft.)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1912-1988 (Boxes 30-33, 35, OV 39; 3.22 linear ft.)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1900-1969 (Boxes 33-35; 0.86 linear ft.)
Series 10: Interview Transcripts, 1943-1968 (Box 34; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 11: Audio and Video Recordings, 1959-1968 (Box 34; 0.25 linear ft.)
Series 12: Artifacts, circa 1930s-circa 1960s (Box 34; 2 items)
Baskin, Leonard, 1922-2000; Delano, Jack; Dugan, Alan; Evans, Walker, 1903-1975; Ferry, W. Hawkins; Francis, Arlene; Friendly, Fred W.; Gusten, Theodore; Hirsch, Joseph, 1910-1981; Kingman, Dong, 1911-; Lange, Dorothea; Lee, Russell, 1903-; Lionni, Leo, 1910-; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-; Martin, John Bartlow, 1915-1987; Mydans, Carl; Nakashima, George, 1905-; Nakashima, Marian; Odets, Clifford, 1906-1963; Osborn, Robert Chesley, 1904-; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957; Robbins, Jerome; Rodman, Selden, 1909-; Rothstein, Arthur, 1915-; Sheeler, Charles, 1883-1965; Smith, David, 1906-1965; Soby, James Thrall, 1906-1979; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987;; Vachon, John, 1914-1975; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Wolcott, Marion Post, 1910-; Zorach, William, 1887-1966; Awards; Drawings; Illustrators--United States; Interviews; Motion pictures (visual works); Painters--United States; Photographers--United States; Photographs; Printmakers--United States; Prints; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video recordings
- Biographical and Family Records, 1879-1984; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 36
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes biographical sketches for Shahn maintained by Downtown Gallery, various award certificates received by Shahn over the course of his career, a 1924 passport for Shahn and his first wife, Tillie Goldstein, and various family legal records including the divorce papers of Ben and Tillie Shahn, copies of Jonathan Shahn's birth certificate and Ezra Shahn's doctorate certificate, and indenture papers for a branch of Bernarda Bryson Shahn's family. Also found in this series are resume details for Bernarda Bryson Shahn and two cards showing her membership in the Author's Guild.
  Arrangement note
  Records are arranged alphabetically by folder title. This series has been scanned in entirety.
  - Award Certificates, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Sketches, circa 1947-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Divorce Papers, Tillie G. Shahn vs. Ben Shahn, 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Identification Documents and Passport, 1924-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Indenture Papers for Members of Nettlefold Family to work for Charles Evans, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    oversized material housed in OV 36
  - Membership Cards, circa 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Records of Shahn Family Members, 1956-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Indenture Papers for Members of Nettlefold Family to work for Charles Evans, 1879 (Box OV 36)
    oversized material scanned with Box 1, F5
- Letters, 1929-1990; Series 2; 14.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-25, 35, OVs 36-38
  This series consists primarily of letters written to Shahn throughout his career from family, friends, artists, business associates, government contacts, universities and colleges, galleries and other art organizations and institutions. Overall, there are very few letters from Shahn to be found, and scattered letters and copies of letters written by him are generally noted in the Container Listing.
  The series includes many letters from artist, writers and colleagues including Leonard Baskin, Mirella Bentivoglio, Alexander Calder, Clifford Odets, Walker Evans, W. H. (Ping) Ferry, Fred Friendly, Dorothea Lange, Leo Lionni, John Bartlow Martin, George and Marian Nakashima, Clifford Odets, Charles Olson, Rudy Pozzati, Diego Rivera, Edwin Rosskam, Jerome Robbins, Selden Rodman, James Thrall Soby, Raphael Soyer and William Carlos Williams. Also found are a number of letters, many of them illustrated, from Robert Osborn, one letter each from Montgomery Clift, Pablo Picasso and Pete Seeger, and two letters from Robert Rauschenberg.
  Documentation of Shahn's career covers his employment with the FSA, the OWI, and the CIO-PAC, his speaking and teaching engagements for many universities and colleges such as Famous Artist Schools, Inc., Harvard University, Princeton University, and the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, and his commercial work for a variety of companies and publications including CBS, Harper's, Pantheon Books, Time, and Container Corporation of America. Files for Downtown Gallery record Edith Halpert's representation of Shahn's work and ultimately the disagreements that led to the dissolution of the dealer-artist relationship in 1968. Documentation of the legal aspects of Shahn's career can be found in letters from his lawyer, Martin Bressler, and include a copy of the letter in which Shahn states his final dissolution of his professional relationship with Halpert, and records of Shahn's legal dealings with Spiral Press, and Arnold Fawcus of Trianon Press. Letters also supplement the Project Files with documentation of some of Shahn's private and public commissions.
  This series also contains letters that Bernarda Bryson Shahn continued to receive after Shahn's death in 1969. These posthumous letters are primarily requests to view Shahn's papers, or inquiries about Shahn and his work.
  The series provides scattered documentation of Bernarda Bryson Shahn's career including her illustration work for Atlantic Monthly, Charles Scribner's Sons, Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc., Grossman Publisher, Inc., and Macmillan Company.
  Letters from Judith Shahn to her parents provide insight into her career as an artist and also into that of her husband, poet Alan Dugan.
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. All correspondents with 5 or more letters associated with their name are housed in a named file. The remaining letters are filed as "Miscellaneous" at the end of the named files for the relevant letter of the alphabet. Named and miscellaneous files are followed by: posthumous letters; letters of correspondents for whom only first names are known; letters with illegible signatures; and unsigned letters respectively.
  This series has been scanned in entirety.
  - A. S. Barnes & Company, Inc., 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aber, Ita (Mrs. M. Joshua), 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Abramowitz, Anita and Max, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Addison Gallery of American Art, 1949-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, Inc., 1967, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Airlie Foundation, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Akron Art Institute, circa 1951-1959, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Albright Art Gallery, Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Aldus Books Limited, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alfred A. Knopf Incorporated, 1937, 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Allan, Elkan, 1950-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1959-1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Association of University Women, 1945-1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1955-1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1943-1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    (includes letter from Shahn)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1935-1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - American Friends of the Hebrew University, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Friends Service Committee, Inc., 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc., 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - American Institute of Architects, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - American Institute of Graphic Arts, 1948-1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - America Jewish Congress (various divisions/chapters), 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - American Judaism, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Amherst College, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Anderson, Don, 1949-1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Appel, Ben and Sophie, circa 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Architects Associated (Richard G. Stein), 1954-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Architectural League of New York, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Archives of American Art, 1962-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Art Academy of Cincinnati, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Art Association of Indianapolis (John Herron Art Institute), 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Art Digest, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Art Directors Club, Inc., 1949-1967, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Art Front (Joe Vogel), circa 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    (includes notes handwritten probably by Shahn)
  - Art in America, 1961-1964, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1941-1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Art News, 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Art Students League of New York, 1950-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Artists and Writers Press, Inc. (Ole Risom), 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Artists' Committee to Free Siqueiros, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Artists Equity Association, Reports and Minutes of Meetings, 1947-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Artists for CORE (Congress on Racial Equality), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Arts, Sciences and Professions, Inc. (various committees), 1945-1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Arwin Galleries Inc., 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Asahi Shimbun, 1981-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Asano, Takeji, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Associated American Artists, 1942-1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Associated Artists of Pittsburgh, 1951-1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Atlantic Monthly Press, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Atlantic Monthly Press, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Atlantic Monthly Press, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Atlantic Monthly Press, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Avant Garde, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ave Maria, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - A, Miscellaneous: A - Ad, 1935-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - A, Miscellaneous: Af - Al, 1943-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - A, Miscellaneous: Ama - American Council, 1937-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - A, Miscellaneous: American Federation - Ams, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - A, Miscellaneous: An - Aq, 1947-1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - A, Miscellaneous: Arc - Art Education, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A, Miscellaneous: Art Gallery - Arts, 1945-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A, Miscellaneous: As, 1946-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - A, Miscellaneous: At - Ay, 1944-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - A, Miscellaneous, Posthumous, 1969-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - A, First Names Only, circa 1956-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Baker, Hollis S., 1953-1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bakwin, Harry and Ruth, 1951-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Balance House (Marshall Lee), 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1950-1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bard College (Bard-St. Stephens), 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Barnard College, Columbia University, 1954-1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Baron, Marshall, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)